Joan K. Jackson papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Joan K. Jackson papers
1946-2016
Ms Coll 54
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
3
Two regular archives boxes and a flat box.
Jackson, Joan K.
Biographical / Historical
Joan K. Jackson, an early expert in alcoholism and the family, was born as Joan Katherine Currie in Parkhill, Ontario, Canada, in 1922. She received her B.A. (1945) and M.A. (1947) in sociology from McGill University where she studied returning Canadian veterans. She married in 1946 Stanley W. Jackson, a veteran, who began the study of medicine at McGill. Joan Jackson received her Ph.D. in (medical) sociology from the University of Washington in 1955. She then joined the Department of Psychiatry where she rose to the level of tenured research associate professor. At the University of Washington, Jackson conducted pioneering research on alcoholism and the family and on alcholism and tuberculosis, and served on various governmental boards. As part of her research she attended Alcoholics Anonymous meetings, starting in 1951, and helped with the wives of alcoholics who were starting Al-Anon in Seattle. She received a coveted five-year research award from NIH. In 1964, at the height of her career, she agreed to leave her faculty position and grant to join her husband, a psychiatrist, who wanted to go to New Haven to study history of medicine. He joined the Psychiaitry Department at Yale and the Section of History of Medicine. She helped him in his career. Joan Jackson became active in alcoholism studies again when she served as a Class A (non-alcoholic) trustee of the General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous from 1983 to 1992.
Scope and Contents
The papers include Joan Jackson's masters' degree research, her masters' thesis, correrspondence, presentations, grant applications, and publications, and a scrapbook documenting her successful career at University of Washington. The second part of the collection documents her role as a Class A Trustee (i.e. non-alcoholic) of the General Study Board of Alcoholics Anonymous from 1983 to 1992, incuding her presentations and publications.
Arrangement
Organized into 4 series: 1. Biographical. 2. Academic career, 1946-1964. 3. Class A Trustee of the General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous, Inc. 4. Scrapbook.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the estate of Joan K. Jackson, 2017.
Alcoholics; Alcoholics' spouses -- Washington (State) -- Seattle; Mental health; Tuberculosis; Alcoholics--Family relationships; Alcoholism--Social aspects; Alcoholism--Study and teaching; Alcoholism -- Washington (State) -- Seattle; Veterans--Canada; Women in science; World War, 1939-1945 -- Social aspects -- Canada; Correspondence; Theses; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sociologists -- Washington (State) -- Seattle; Jackson, Stanley W., 1920-; Alcoholics Anonymous; Al-Anon Family Group Headquarters, Inc. (History); McGill University. Department of Sociology and Anthropology; University of Washington. Department of Psychiatry
- Biographical, Series 1
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Obituary written by Joan Jackson; other obituaries (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Joan Jackson wrote her own obituary ca. 2014-2015, before the death or her last beagle. This is the copy she gave to the archivist, Toby Appel. The New Haven Register obituary is based in this.
  - Chapter, "Dr. Joan K. Jackson," in Women Pioneers in 12 Step Recovery, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Folder contains two drafts of the chapter on Jackson by Bob Pearson who interviewed Jackson, and related correspondence. The final publication was Charlotte Hunter, Billye Jones, and Joan Ziegler, Women Pioneers in 12 Step Recovery (Center City, Minnesota: Hazelden Foundation, 1999).
- Academic career, 1946-1964; Series 2
  Joan Jackson's academic career spans her research for her master's degree at McGill University in 1946-1947, her subsequent work for the Department of Sociology and Anthropology at McGill until 1951, and the period 1951-1964 during which Jackson received her Ph.D. in medical sociology at Washington University in 1955 and became a member of the faculty of the Department of Psychiatry. In Seattle, Jackson became familiar with the work of Alcoholics Anonymous and the beginnings of Al-Anon in the city. Jackson put together a scrapbook from this period which is in Box 3.
  - Bernice Gold and Joan K. Jackson, "Psychological Adjustment of Ex-Service Personnel," National Research Council Canada, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Carbon typescript, 282 pages. The heading on the first page is "Role of Attitudes in the Adjustment of Ex-Service Personnel." The authors were master's degree candidates in Sociology at McGill University. Jackson was working for the National Research Council of Canada under the direction of Dr. Ewen Cameron during 1945 and 1946. Jackson's master's thesis at McGill (1947) was on this topic. See next folder.
  - Joan K. Jackson, "Rehabilitation: A National, Institutional, and Individual Crisis," Master's thesis, Department of Sociology, McGill University, 1947 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
    On the rehabilitation of Canadian veterans after World War II, especially public and government attitudes, the psychology of the veteran, and the veteran in the University. See previous folder.
  - Carl A Dawson and Warner E. Gettys, An Introduction to Sociology, 3rd ed., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    After completing her master's degree, Jackson stayed on working for the Department of Sociology an Anthropology while her husband finished medical school. This book, published by Ronald Press, New York, was Jackson's underlined and annotated copy. It was inscribed by Carl J. Dawson, Chairman of the Department of Sociology and Anthropology, McGill University: "Mrs. Joan Currie Jackson whose help made the publication of this text-book possible." The authors wrote in the last sentences of the introduction, "Mrs. Joan Currie Jackson, research assistant in the McGill Department of Sociology and Anthropology, did some of the original writing and has been associated with the work of proofreading. Her competency is reflected on every page of this edition."
  - Poem about Joan Jackson, ca. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Poem about Jackson by C.S.J. that notes that Joan is a poet and the she has been married for three years. Folder also contains an undated issue of First Statement: A Magazine for Young Canadian Writers.
  - Correspondence, Department of Psychiatry, University of Washington, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - NIH grant application, "Socio-Cultural Studies of Mental Health and Disease", 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondence and the grant application.
  - Part of a grant application/report on alcoholism and the family, ca. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    The report discusses what little research has been done on alcoholism and the family and what Joan Jackson and her collaborators were doing. At this time, alcoholics were almost all men. Research on the families of alcoholics had focused on the wives of alcoholics. Children of alcoholics had not yet been studied.
  - NSF grants and consultancies, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NIH Research Career Development Award, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Jackson won a coveted NIH Career Development Award. At that point, she held the rank of Research Associate Professor (Sociology) in the Department of Psychiatry, University of Washington. The award which, paid Jackson's full salary and research costs, was to last from February 1, 1964 to January 31, 1969.
  - Presentations, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "Some Characteristics of Tuberculous Alcoholics," "N.T. Assn.," Kansas City, May 8, 1957; "Personnel Interpersonal Relationships and the Patient," presented at a nursing conference, November 13, 1957 (date on the paper). The original folder tab had the date of November 15, 1957.
  - Presentations, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    "Research on Alcoholism and Tuberculosis," California Tuberculosis and Health Association, San Mateo, California, April 11, 1958.
  - Presentations, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Presentation on alcoholism for the SCA Workshop (Seattle Conference on Alcoholism), January 14, 1960.
  - Presentations, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Kate L. Kogan and Joan K. Jackson, "Research Perspectives in Alcohol Studies and Alcoholism: Alcoholism and the Family," to be presented at the Western Psychological Association Meeting, June 16, 1961; Joan K. Jackson, "Alcoholism and the Family," presented at the Mental Health Research Institute, Western State Hospital, Steilacoom, Washington, August 18, 1961.
  - Presentations, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Joan K. Jackson, "Action and Recommendations to Date," presented at the Mayor's Conference on Alcoholism at the University of Washington, November 29, 1962.
  - Joan K. Jackson, "Al-Anon in Seattle, Washington, U.S.A.", ca. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Joan Jackson was in Seattle during the early years of Al-Anon in the city and in the United States. What began as a small "AA auxiliary" group of wives of alcoholics grew into several chapters of Al-Anon. This paper traces this history.
  - Unpublished presentation/paper on AA, ca. 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Joan K. Jackson, "A Second Look at Alcoholics Anonymous." This paper was addressed to doctors, psychologists, and others treating alcoholism.
  - "Research on Alcoholism and the Family," New Zealand Al-Anon, 1963, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Apparently, a group of people representing the New Zealand Al-Anon visited Seattle to meet Al-Anon members in Seattle and study the research taking place at the University of Washington. This paper (author unknown) was published in Inventory, a New Zealand Al-Anon magazine, in 1965.
  - Barbara Courtney, paper on Al-Anon, 1961 August (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Barbara Courtney was a student of Joan Jackson and a member of Al-Anon. She became a social worker.
  - Washington State Department of Health, Hospital Management of Alcoholics, Joan K. Jackson, co-PI, ca. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Washington State Department of Health, Community Attitudes and Knowledge of Alcoholism, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Jackson was a consultant for this report,
  - Clippings on Joan K. Jackson, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Articles, 1953-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    This folder includes only a few of Jackson's articles, among them the classic "The Skid Row Alcoholic"(1953). Some of her articles were widely reprinted. In 1989, upon request, her seminal article, "The Adjustment of the Family to the Crisis of Alcoholism" (1954), was republished with a new introduction by Jackson in a pamphlet series by the Center of Alcohol Studies, Rutgers University.
  - Requests to republish articles, 1965-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Joan Jackson from parents, 1953, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Three items from John C. Currie and Ruth Fenn Currie. The first item is a telegram of congratulations. The second is a letter from Mrs. Currie concerning Jackson's departure to New Haven. Her mother wrote, "Find another way to use your training and experience -- You can't just lightly abandon your alcoholics to become plain Mrs. Stanley Jackson (full-time homemaker)."
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 14)
    The folder contains two photographs taken at a graduation ceremony. One may be of Jackson's parents. The folder also contains an informal note of congratulations on her passing all her examinations, signed Francis(?).
  - Report of the Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, 1976 June (Box 2, Folder 15)
    This published report, saved by Jackson, does not mention her but shows how much the study of alcoholism at the University of Washington had expanded since Jackson's time there.
- Class A Trustee of the General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous, Inc., Series 3
  Joan Jackson served as a Class A Trustee of the General Services Board of Alcoholics Anonymous from 1983 to 1992. The General Services Board was the central governing body of AA. It consisted of 14 alcoholic trustees (most sober for many years), known as Class B trustees, and 7 Class A trustees. The Class A trustees were non-alcoholics who were selected for their knowledge of alcoholism. Jackson was soon recognized for her ability to teach and write, and from 1985 on, she was asked to participate in the orientation of new trustees. The collection contains several of her presentations, programs of meetings, some presentations by others, her testimony before Congress, and her analysis in 2006 of whether it was appropriate for an alcoholic trustee to serve as Chairman of the Board.
  - General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous, Orientation of new trustees, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Folder includes the program, correspondence, and Jackson's presentation, "The Concepts and Their Relation to the Work of the Trustees." Also included is the program of the annual meeting in 1985.
  - General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous, Orientation of new trustees, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Folder includes the program, Jackson's presentations, "The Class A Trustee" and "The Concepts and Their Relationship to the Work of the Trustees," and correspondence from the A.A. General Service Office and from Robert Pearson.
  - General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous, Orientation session, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Letter from Lois Fisher, Assistant Secretary, General Service Board, praising Jackson's participation in the orientation session in 1987.
  - General Sharing Session, AA, 1988 October 10 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Program and Jackson's presentation, "The Committee System: How It Works."
  - Joan Jackson's testimony on AA before the Committee on Governmental Affairs, United States Senate, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Photocopy of the Hearing on Causes and Consequences of Alcohol Abuse. The hearings contain both Jackson's testimony and her prepared statement.
  - General Service Board of Alcoholics Anonymous, Orientation session, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Correspondence, program, and Jackson's presentation, "Communications/Challenges."
  - Regional Forum, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Joan K. Jackson presentation, Role of the Class A Trustee. Included with the text is a cover letter to "Joe," sending the paper as requested.
  - The A.A. Service Manual combined with Twelve Concepts for World Service, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    This edition reflects actions of the 1990 General Service Conference.
  - Presentation by an African-American trustee, ca. 1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    The title is "Alcoholics Anonymous is a Tapestry that has a Million Threads." Jackson nted that the presentation was possibly given at a Board Weekend.
  - Joan Jackson, article on her experience with AA for The AA Grapevine, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Donation to the Al-Anon Archives, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Jackson donated material, described in this folder, on the early history of Al-Anon in Seattle. She told the archivist (Toby Appel) that the material was lost. See also Box 2, Folder 4. A copy of this article was also given to the Al-Anon archives. Some of the photographs came from her scrapbook. See Box 3.
  - Jackson's response to the possibility of a Class B trustee serving a chairman of the General Services Board, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - About AA: A Newsletter for Professionals, Summer/Fall 2014 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    An article, "The Role of A.A.'s Class A (nonalcoholic Trustees," quoted Joan Jackson's earlier presentation on the topic.
  - Drafts of a review of Working Sober for the Bulletin of the History of Medicine (Box 2, Folder 29)
    The folder contains correspondence, drafts, and a copy of the published review of William J. Sonnenstuhl, Working Sober: The Transformation of an Occupational Drinking Culture (Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University Press, 1996).
- Scrapbook, ca. 1951-1964; Series 4 (Box 3)
  Scrapbook that Jackson put together after leaving the University of Washington. It contains correspondence thanking her and wishing her well, photographs, clippings and other references to her work, and miscellany. Photographs of Al-Anon members were removed and given to the Al-Anon archives.